so I wanted to ask about becoming an
Aryan higher or becoming one with the right
higher or becoming one with the right
view way entering jars all these things
accidental can you stumble into them you
stumble into right view and then losers
so forget about it will forget about can
you forget how not the slightest other
words if there were the truth we
wouldn't need the Buddha and his
teachings and all the teachings he done
and all the instruction and all the
repetitive effort encouragement and
everything else the Buddha wouldn't be
going around saying whatever's to be
obtained by manly effort manly
dedication Manny determination that's
what I would think yeah we say oh look I
stumbled upon this how did you do it
exactly so if if it's the right
understanding you will know how you've
done it because it's knowing how to do
it means that's what the right
understanding is so the right view means
understanding what the right view is
that's your right view it's all the
experience you had that felt right but
you don't quite know what it was or how
I was or how you came how it came to be
same with jhana same with any other
establishment of composure and your mind
and discernment comprehension that's why
the Buddha the suitors would say like I
think of many different occasions but
one I'm thinking of I think he was about
venerable sariputta when when he was
going through the various establishments
of mind with like this sermon a
reflection he says knowingly these
states knowingly these experiences have
been discerned knowingly they were
present knowingly those seized yes
knowingly busy with full understanding
for their duration ah this is this is
what I says this is freedom from
sensuality this is freedom from from
from your will oh this is the right view
that's that's what Buddha said so to
ponder when he described so deep honor I
think in that's
you Taneka he was who saw the my sodium
is one who knows that he knows and it's
not just just joking around or or saying
something funny no that's that that was
the most accurate description he knows
that he knows so it's a reflexive
knowledge upon his knowledge Oh full
understanding it's not something
happened to him they fell right and then
he spent next six months trying to
interpret it in a pleasing manner and
then decided that he must be a sort
opponent because of that experience it's
basically putting the foot in the cart
in front of the horse as in through
discerning where the right context is to
discerning where the right view is you
can get then to do it rightly by knowing
the right context but you can't
accidentally do it rightly and then
induce the context on account of it so
the wrong view is abandoned not through
like accidentally doing the right things
and then you'll also this must be that
right view the wrong view is abandoned
through the standing with the right view
is all understanding where the wrong
view is why wrong view is wrong hmm
that's what he would have said he knows
that he knows or he said he understands
skillful as skillful he understands
right as right and he understands wrong
as wrong he understands means that
context remains unchanged imperturbable
regardless of what the experience is on
a particular level but for most people
is the particular level experience that
they're chasing some novelty releases
and energies and whatnot and clarity's
of mind that occurred on account of
something whatever and then they try to
try to read into it and that's why mean
it's basically put in the second which
is the first and that's when the suitors
those who did get the review would say
that to the Buddha oh it is like putting
the first which should have been first
that which I was placed in second you
put it to be first
I understand or turning things they've
been upside down
it's that perversion of the basic owed
me first everything else second but you
realize everything else is first I am
second in regard to my experience as a
whole so whether you had experience that
you never had before this great release
of energy and and compassion and loving
kindness and peace that's absolutely
fine but what is that in your experience
oh it was just a pleasing peaceful
experience great he's that understanding
in regard to it do I know exactly why it
came to be how it came to be do I
understand it that it skillful as in
what it would have said to understand
skillful is skillful or am I just
enjoying the fact that he was pleasing
to me so if there is no understanding of
the nature that state means you are
still regarding yourself as the most
important thing isn't this happened to
me and that's why it's special but if
you start putting everything in question
including the most peaceful experiences
you had you will then start questioning
your own existence through that you will
be refusing to place your gratuitous
notion of self as the center of that
experience and by that I mean you had a
novelty peaceful experience it was very
pleasing but then you okay so what is
what are the characteristics of this
experience do I know how it came about
not quite do I know how long it will
stay not quite do I know why is it good
except that it's pleasing for me Oh am I
also trying to to prolong it will it be
affected if it changes will I suffer on
account of it disappearing all these
things would be sort of pointing at the
context you need to discern and as the
thing context is not in particular
manifestation of the things it's a
background of it
that's why context is on the level of
proper mindfulness as we spoke before so
if all these questions you get to
realize okay so this peaceful state yeah
it's obviously it's my
but much less unwholesome than you know
sensuality or any other types of
pleasure I know but then at the same
time it has a reason for me in my
experience I have no control over it I
don't know how I came about I did not
create it
let those questions in do let those
characteristics endure a bit don't jump
in the answers of conclusions just feel
that as the state of your being okay so
there's this Pleasant but I don't I came
about and then naturally you will be
more cautious about what you'll be more
cautious in regard to losing sight of it
you'll be more cautious in regard to
sort of gratuitously at face value
wanting it longer protecting it because
he came to be and had nothing to do with
you yeah it's pleasing but pleasure then
yeah it's pleasing but pleasure then
came to be has nothing to do with you in
other words if you don't know sight of
it you're not gonna get blindly attached
to it
to put it simply and if you're not lying
attached true then you won't be
gratuitously blindly defending it or
trying to like squeeze the butt you read
in the suit as an interpreter
experienced in that manner they won't be
need for it if you truly understood it
you understood whether suitors talk
about it on the basis of that experience
but if you haven't truly understood it
then means you need to spend time tying
loose ends and and no this is maybe what
that meant or know that like a din no
point during that tying up loose ends do
you crack it do you question your
experience as in that experience of
novelty of peace you had that's it
that's it that's a fact now it's just a
question of finding the right
interpretation for it and what I'm
saying is that's a completely wrong way
around to understanding what the right
interpretation is you get to recognize
but the right experiences are that's why
I thought about you or any other
establishment emetics cannot be done by
accident that's where you need other ins
of another and faith in that and
properly attending to it because without
another answer without the external
criteria that you took on faith
how can you repeat something sufficient
amount of times
which is many times without any apparent
result to it why would you repeat it
it's just impossible it seemed like
statistically impossible so even in
theory unless you know that something
should be repeated and adhere to and
unless you understand it and unless you
have faith in it you cannot possibly do
that so Fisher mount of time because
there is no apparent result so that's
why you cannot establish any of those
things accidentally and if something
accidentally happens means yeah it
happened on the level of particular
experience but that's not what matters
what matters is understanding of it the
context I'm talking about so that's why
the context comes first
that's why the right view comes first
the whole Noble Eightfold Path is rooted
in the right view every single factor of
it no other way around not like I do
this I do this then I do this then I do
this then I do this
oh look I must be doing it rightly
through knowing what's doing it rightly
you get to recognize the doing of of
right things and that's you know you
might even be surprised what you thought
was peaceful and lofty once you develop
the right context you realize actually
wasn't and things that you never kind of
gave them a second look you realize no
that was actually closer to the right
view but you can only have that criteria
when you have the context that can judge
that criteria from and the context is
something that's understood on the basis
of things you experience not something
that's right into it so if you want to
develop something you need to have a
overall picture of what you're trying to
develop if you want to build something
you need to have an overall picture what
you're trying to build and then see what
matches it through your efforts not like
to start building left and right and
suddenly miraculously becomes that thing
but you have no idea how you arrived at
it how can you build a house if you
don't have a notion of what house is
and again that's something if a person
were to self question you will become a
parent how can I be how can i free
myself from suffering if I don't
understand what freedom from suffering
is if I just use criteria of my current
feeling towards freedom of suffering
how can you free yourself from suffering
when only suffering is necessary
basically sorry when only the necessity
of suffering is your only criteria so I
don't know what to do in terms of
freeing myself from suffering but I'm
doing all these things to free myself of
suffering but you don't know how where
and why
would those things for you from
suffering you just hope that through
doing these random things the context of
freeing from suffering will be reached
so that's I mean no amount of methods
techniques or whatever like just through
sheer doing can suddenly bring the
revelation trying to discern the
revelation the right view that's what
can bring the right view and then
whatever you do through it will be right
but not other way around
you're not going to concoct the right
view through randomly doing these
separate things they then magically just
just create this Frankenstein off of you
there's a difference between like my
opinion yeah absolutely
again if you are unaware of the context
of your own situation as in fundamental
context of MI free from suffering am I
not free from suffering that's it that's
the basis and you don't need to go
anywhere further from that that can
remain the criteria throughout whether
your petition or aria until you become
another and am I completely free from
suffering or not but if you're not aware
of that then yeah your opinions would be
basically a second that it kind of
induced points of view on account of
taking your experience for granted so
instead of your opinions questioning
your experience your opinions are just
being built on top of your experience so
that's what I mean like people would
have these like genuine experiences of
you know Southern peace or release
something but instead of okay that's
good there is a hope that I can develop
this piece but instead of recognizing
that that can only be developed through
full understanding of the nature of it
they don't question it they just take it
as it happened that's it now it must be
real forever so now it's just a question
of sort of defending it protecting it or
prolonging it through trying to
manipulate the environment and go on a
longer retreat and then do this and
avoid talking to people and to not
disturb your peace but you realize what
you're defending is not even your peace
you're defending defending that
experience at all which if you were to
look closer you would realize it has a
reason on its own with its own
characteristics and science and context
and you just took it for granted and
it's yours why cuz he was very agreeable
to you that's what most people who even
commit years and years to meditation the
end of meditating with their sensuality
as in sensuality is the base criteria
for the meditation what is agreeable
what's disagreeable now you cannot that
is just a necessary way how you have to
start but one thing is to have that as a
necessary basis in other words
petitioner has to start somehow and it's
not going to be right but another thing
is to never grow out of it
so how can how can we know we are making
progress again context whether you free
from suffering or not he's what you're
doing he's all your experiences you had
as a result of your like whatever
intense meditations in pondering on the
teachings that's so fine but overall
Emma now more free from suffering than I
was before
will I be more affected or will I be
less affected or will I be affected at
all by by by things that would and again
oh I'm not affected right now nobody
imagine you imagine your loved ones
dying around you imagine you losing your
senses your health getting sick loss of
wealth loss of home loss or whatever
imagine it and see is there fear in
regard to it if there is a fear in
regard to it if there is like I wanna
look at this you can't then at the same
time say oh but I'm free from suffering
yeah that's what mean if you start
developing that context through their
questioning you're gonna start
developing self honesty as well you can
ask a lot of people do you suffer yeah
and a lot of people I know but it's more
like in the past when I was a child
didn't know what I was doing I was
suffering things were new to me
sure but now I'm older I can deal with
things much basic yeah so you need to
upgrade your context that's what me yeah
I don't suffer now okay that's fine
that's your first answer now ask a
further question why am I not suffering
is it because I'm an arahant or is it
because there's nothing currently
inducing suffering in me if your answer
it oh it's because I'm in our hunt great
you don't need to do everything anything
ever again
you're done you wouldn't be even
listening to this talk then but if your
answer is well probably still could
suffer in some extreme scenarios means
you can't then say that you're free from
nature suffering because there is no
extreme scenario for somebody who is
free from suffering somebody who is free
from the nature of suffering somebody
who is free from liability to suffering
cannot suffer on any count on
of any particular suffering big or small
extreme or not he cannot suffer so by
keeping that context in the mind you
keep your practice along the right lines
you won't stop making the effort you
won't get complacent nor will you get
sort of deluded on account of your own
you know attainments and whatnot
experiences you had then people told you
there must have been that thing or this
thing or whatever if someone needs to
tell you what that must have been means
you don't really know what it was if you
don't know what it was how can you say
you're free from doubt in regard to it
how can you say that you know that you
know I know that I know nothing like
some blind kind of religious
fundamentalism but just know genuinely
understand how it came to be I
understand how it ceased I understand
what it is I understand wholesome is
wholesome no method or technique can
teach you that except your own effort
and self questioning and reflection with
the guidance of the sutras and the
Buddha's instruction